# **Ian Char**

6105 Gates Center, 5000 Forbes Ave. Pittsburgh, PA 15213 ianchar.com ichar@cs.cmu.edu

RESEARCH INTERESTS My main research interests are focused around deep reinforcement learning, decision making under uncertainty, and uncertainty quantification. I am particularly interested in developing algorithms for engineering and the sciences.

**EDUCATION** 

Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA, United States

Ph.D. in Machine Learning

August 2018 - Present

Advisor: Jeff Schneider

University of Colorado Boulder, Boulder, CO, United States

M.S./B.S. in Applied Math and B.S. in Computer Science

August 2013 - May 2018

Advisor: Manuel Lladser

UGRD GPA: 4.00, GRAD GPA: 3.88

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA, United States

Control for Nuclear Fusion

August 2018 - Present

My research efforts during my Ph.D. have all revolved around learning a controller for a nuclear fusion reactor. In particular, I have worked on Bayesian optimization, reinforcement learning, and uncertainty quantification.

## University of Colorado Boulder, Boulder, CO, United States

Stochastic Analysis of Minimal Automata

August 2016 - May 2018

For my master's thesis, I worked with Professor Manuel Lladser to analyze the growth rate of a particular class of minimal deterministic finite automaton. We derived a high probability bound on the number of states that grows polynomially.

WORK EXPERIENCE

## **Google**, Software Engineering Intern

May 2017 - August 2017

- Integrated several components into simulation to evaluate Google's supply chain.
- Leveraged simulation framework to conduct several studies on how varying several quantities such as weeks of supply and lead time affect overall performance.

#### **Terra Bella (Google)**, Software Engineering Intern

May 2016 - August 2016

- Analyzed historical weather datasets in order to help predict the supply of satellite imagery that could be provided.
- Ingested a new dataset with over 54,000 images into Google Earth Engine for internal use.

## **Google**, Software Engineering Intern

May 2015 - August 2015

- Created an interactive tutorial in order to teach users about AdWords' Conversion Tracking.
- Implemented an Android package name search service in Conversion Tracking.

#### **SOFTWARE**

## **Uncertainty Toolbox**, https://uncertainty-toolbox.github.io/

2020

- Open source python library for predictive uncertainty quantification, calibration, metrics, and visualizations.
- Currently has more than 1.5k stars on GitHub.

## **PUBLICATIONS**

## CONFERENCES AND JOURNALS

<u>Char, I.</u>, Abbate, J., Bardóczi, L., Boyer, M., Chung, Y., Conlin, R., ... & Schneider, J. (2023, June). "Offline Model-Based Reinforcement Learning for Tokamak Control." In Learning for Dynamics and Control Conference (pp. 1357-1372). PMLR.

Li, X., Mehta, V., Kirschner, J., Char, I., Neiswanger, W., Schneider, J., ... & Bogunovic, I. (2022). "Near-optimal Policy Identification in Active Reinforcement Learning." International Conference on Learning Representations, 2023.

Mehta, V., <u>Char, I.</u>, Abbate, J., Conlin, R., Boyer, M., Ermon, S., ... & Neiswanger, W. (2022). "Exploration via planning for information about the optimal trajectory." Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, 35, 28761-28775.

Apostolopoulou, I., <u>Char, I.</u>, Rosenfeld, E. & Dubrawski, A. "Deep Attentive Variational Inferences." International Conference on Learning Representations, 2021.

Chung, Y., Neiswanger, W., Char, I. & Schneider, J. "Beyond Pinball Loss: Quantile Methods for Calibrated Uncertainty Quantification." In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, 2021.

Mehta V., <u>Char, I.</u>, Neiswanger, W., Chung, Y., Nelson, A. O., Boyer, M., Kolemen E. & Schneider, J. "Neural Dynamics Systems: Balancing Structure and Flexibility in Physical Prediction." IEEE Conference on Decision and Control, 2021.

<u>Char, I.</u>, Chung, Y., Neiswanger, W., Kandasamy, K., Nelson, A. O., Boyer, M., Kolemen, E. & Schneider, J. "Offline contextual bayesian optimization." In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, 2019.

<u>Char, I.</u>, & Lladser, M. E. "Stochastic Analysis of Minimal Automata Growth for Generalized Strings." Methodology and Computing in Applied Probability, 2019.

## TECHNICAL REPORTS AND WORKSHOPS

<u>Char, I.</u> & Schneider, J. "PID-Inspired Inductive Biases for Deep Reinforcement Learning in Partially Observable Control Tasks" https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.05891 (In Submission)

Igoe, C., Chung, Y., <u>Char, I.</u> & Schneider, J. "How Useful are Gradients for OOD Detection Really?" https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.10439

<u>Char, I.\*</u>, Mehta, V.\*, Villaflor, A., Dolan, J. & Schneider, J. "BATS: Best Action Trajectory Stitching." NeurIPS 2021 Offline Reinforcement Learning Workshop.

Chung, Y., Char, I., Guo H., Schneider, J. & Neiswanger, W. "Uncertainty Toolbox: an Open-Source Library for Assessing Visualizing and Improving Uncertainty Quantification." ICML 2021 Uncertainty and Robustness in Deep Learning Workshop.

Chung, Y., <u>Char, I.</u>, Neiswanger, W., Kandasamy, K., Nelson, A. O., Boyer, M., Kolemen, E. & Schneider, J. "Offline contextual bayesian optimization for nuclear fusion." NeurIPS 2019 Machine Learning and the Physical Sciences Workshop.

## AWARDS Machine Learning Department Teaching Assistant of the Year

2021-2022

# NSF Graduate Research Fellowship

2018

#### Chancellor's Award

2018

Awarded by the chancellor of the University of Colorado for highest GPA university-wide.

#### TEACHING

#### 10-606/607: Mathematical/Computational Foundations for Machine Learning

Fall 2021

Carnegie Mellon University

**Teaching Assistant** 

## 10-716: Advanced Machine Learning: Theory and Methods

Spring 2020

Carnegie Mellon University

Teaching Assistant

# **APPM 4350: Fourier Series and Boundary Value Problems**

**Fall 2016** 

University of Colorado Boulder

Teaching Assistant

[Updated 2023-07-14]